In the clustering problem we are
在聚类问题中
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
given an unlabeled data
我们有未加标签的数据
set and we would like
我们希望有一个算法
to have an algorithm automatically
能够自动的
group the data into coherent
把这些数据分成
subsets or into coherent clusters for us.
有紧密关系的子集或是簇
The K Means algorithm is by
K均值 (K-means) 算法
far the most popular, by
是现在最为广泛使用的
far the most widely used clustering
聚类方法
algorithm, and in this
那么在这个视频中
video I would like to tell
我将会告诉你
you what the K Means Algorithm is and how it works.
什么是K均值算法以及它是怎么运作的
The K means clustering algorithm is best illustrated in pictures.
K均值算法最好用图来表达
Let's say I want to take
如图所示
an unlabeled data set like
现在我有一些
the one shown here, and I
没加标签的数据
want to group the data into two clusters.
而我想将这些数据分成两个簇
If I run the K Means clustering
现在我执行K均值算法
algorithm, here is what
方法是这样的
I'm going to do. The first step is to randomly initialize two
首先我随机选择两个点
points, called the cluster centroids.
这两个点叫做聚类中心 (cluster centroids)
So, these two crosses here,
就是图上边的两个叉
these are called the Cluster Centroids
这两个就是聚类中心
and I have two of them
为什么要两个点呢
because I want to group my data into two clusters.
因为我希望聚出两个类
K Means is an iterative algorithm and it does two things.
K均值是一个迭代方法 它要做两件事情
First is a cluster assignment
第一个是簇分配
step, and second is a move centroid step.
第二个是移动聚类中心
So, let me tell you what those things mean.
我来告诉你这两个是干嘛的
The first of the two steps in the
在K均值算法的每次循环中
loop of K means, is this cluster assignment step.
第一步是要进行簇分配
What that means is that, it's
这就是说
going through each of the
我要遍历所有的样本
examples, each of these green
就是图上所有的绿色的点
dots shown here and depending
然后依据
on whether it's closer to the
每一个点
red cluster centroid or the
是更接近红色的这个中心
blue cluster centroid, it is going
还是蓝色的这个中心
to assign each of the
来将每个数据点
data points to one of the two cluster centroids.
分配到两个不同的聚类中心中
Specifically, what I mean
具体来讲
by that, is to go through your
我指的是
data set and color each
对数据集中的所有点
of the points either red or
依据他们
blue, depending on whether
更接近红色这个中心
it is closer to the red
还是蓝色这个中心
cluster centroid or the blue
进行染色
cluster centroid, and I've done that in this diagram here.
染色之后的结果如图所示
So, that was the cluster assignment step.
以上就是簇分配的步骤
The other part of K means, in the
K均值的另一部分
loop of K means, is the move
是要移动聚类中心
centroid step, and what
具体的操作方法
we are going to do is, we
是这样的
are going to take the two cluster centroids,
我们将两个聚类中心
that is, the red cross and
也就是说红色的叉
the blue cross, and we are
和蓝色的叉
going to move them to the average
移动到
of the points colored the same colour.
和它一样颜色的那堆点的均值处
So what we are going
那么我们要做的是
to do is look at all the
找出所有红色的点
red points and compute the
计算出它们的均值
average, really the mean
就是所有红色的点
of the location of all the red points,
平均下来的位置
and we are going to move the red cluster centroid there.
然后我们就把红色点的聚类中心移动到这里
And the same things for the
蓝色的点也是这样
blue cluster centroid, look at all
找出所有蓝色的点
the blue dots and compute their
计算它们的均值
mean, and then move the blue cluster centroid there.
把蓝色的叉放到那里
So, let me do that now.
那我们现在就这么做
We're going to move the cluster centroids as follows
我们将按照图上所示这么移动
and I've now moved them to their new means.
现在两个中心都已经移动到新的均值那里了
The red one moved like that
你看
and the blue one moved
蓝色的这么移动
like that and the red one moved like that.
红色的这么移动
And then we go back to another cluster
然后我们就会进入下一个
assignment step, so we're again
簇分配
going to look at all of
我们重新检查
my unlabeled examples and depending
所有没有标签的样本
on whether it's closer the red or the blue cluster centroid,
依据它离红色中心还是蓝色中心更近一些
I'm going to color them either red or blue.
将它染成红色或是蓝色
I'm going to assign each point
我要将每个点
to one of the two cluster centroids, so let me do that now.
分配给两个中心的某一个 就像这么做
And so the colors of some of the points just changed.
你看某些点的颜色变了
And then I'm going to do another move centroid step.
然后我们又要移动聚类中心
So I'm going to compute the
于是我计算
average of all the blue points,
蓝色点的均值
compute the average of all
还有红色点的均值
the red points and move my
然后就像图上所表示的
cluster centroids like this, and
移动两个聚类中心
so, let's do that again.
来我们再来一遍
Let me do one more cluster assignment step.
下面我还是要做一次簇分配
So colour each point red
将每个点
or blue, based on what it's
染成红色或是蓝色
closer to and then
依然根据它们离那个中心近
do another move centroid step and we're done.
然后是移动中心 你看就像这样
And in fact if you
实际上
keep running additional iterations of
如果你从这一步开始
K means from here the
一直迭代下去
cluster centroids will not change
聚类中心是不会变的
any further and the colours of
并且
the points will not change any
那些点的颜色也不会变
further. And so, this is
在这时
the, at this point,
我们就能说
K means has converged and it's
K均值方法已经收敛了
done a pretty good job finding
在这些数据中找到两个簇
the two clusters in this data.
K均值表现的很好
Let's write out the K means algorithm more formally.
来我们用更加规范的格式描述K均值算法
The K means algorithm takes two inputs.
K均值算法接受两个输入
One is a parameter K,
第一个是参数K
which is the number of clusters
表示你想从数据中
you want to find in the data.
聚类出的簇的个数
I'll later say how we might
我一会儿会讲到
go about trying to choose k, but
我们可以怎样选择K
for now let's just say that
这里呢 我们只是说
we've decided we want a
我们已经确定了
certain number of clusters and we're
需要几个簇
going to tell the algorithm how many
然后我们要告诉这个算法
clusters we think there are in the data set.
我们觉得在数据集里有多少个簇
And then K means also
K均值同时要
takes as input this sort
接收另外一个输入
of unlabeled training set of
那就是只有 x 的
just the Xs and
没有标签 y 的训练集
because this is unsupervised learning, we
因为这是非监督学习
don't have the labels Y anymore.
我们用不着 y
And for unsupervised learning of
同时在非监督学习的
the K means I'm going to
K均值算法里
use the convention that XI
我们约定
is an RN dimensional vector.
x(i) 是一个n维向量
And that's why my training examples
这就是
are now N dimensional rather N plus one dimensional vectors.
训练样本是 n 维而不是 n+1 维的原因
This is what the K means algorithm does.
这就是K均值算法
The first step is that it
第一步是
randomly initializes k cluster
随机初始化 K 个聚类中心
centroids which we will
记作
call mu 1, mu 2, up
μ1, μ2 一直到 μk
to mu k. And so
就像之前
in the earlier diagram, the
图中所示
cluster centroids corresponded to the
聚类中心对应于
location of the red cross
红色叉和蓝色叉
and the location of the blue cross.
所在的位置
So there we had two cluster
于是我们有两个聚类中心
centroids, so maybe the red
按照这样的记法
cross was mu 1
红叉是 μ1
and the blue cross was mu
蓝叉是 μ2
2, and more generally we would have
通常情况下
k cluster centroids rather than just 2.
我们可能会有比2要多的聚类中心
Then the inner loop
K均值的内部循环
of k means does the following,
是这样的
we're going to repeatedly do the following.
我们会重复做下面的事情
First for each of
首先
my training examples, I'm going
对于每个训练样本
to set this variable CI
我们用变量 c(i) 表示
to be the index 1 through
K个聚类中心中最接近 x(i) 的
K of the cluster centroid closest to XI.
那个中心的下标
So this was my cluster assignment
这就是簇分配
step, where we
这个步骤
took each of my examples and
我先将每个样本
coloured it either red
依据它离那个聚类中心近
or blue, depending on which
将其染成
cluster centroid it was closest to.
红色或是蓝色
So CI is going to be
所以 c(i) 是一个
a number from 1 to
在1到 K 之间的数
K that tells us, you
而且它表明
know, is it closer to the
这个点到底是
red cross or is it
更接近红色叉
closer to the blue cross,
还是蓝色叉
and another way of writing this
另一种表达方式是
is I'm going to,
我想要计算 c(i)
to compute Ci, I'm
那么
going to take my Ith
我要用第i个样本x(i)
example Xi and and
然后
I'm going to measure it's distance
计算出这个样本
to each of my cluster centroids,
距离所有K个聚类中心的距离
this is mu and then
这是 μ
lower-case k, right, so
以及小写的k
capital K is the total
大写的 K 表示
number centroids and I'm going
所有聚类中心的个数
to use lower case k here
小写的 k 则是
to index into the different centroids.
不同的中心的下标
But so, Ci is going to, I'm going
我希望的是
to minimize over my values
在所有K个中心中
of k and find the
找到一个k
value of K that minimizes this
使得xi到μk的距离
distance between Xi and the
是xi到所有的聚类中心的距离中
cluster centroid, and then,
最小的那个
you know, the
也就是说
value of k that minimizes
k的值使这个最小
this, that's what gets set in
这就是计算ci的方法
Ci. So, here's
这里还有
another way of writing out what Ci is.
另外的表示ci的方法
If I write the norm between
我用xi减μk的范数
Xi minus Mu-k,
来表示
then this is the distance between
这是第i个训练样本
my ith training example
到聚类中心μk
Xi and the cluster centroid
的距离
Mu subscript K, this is--this
注意
here, that's a lowercase K. So uppercase
我这里用的是小写的k
K is going to be
大写的K
used to denote the total
大写的k表示
number of cluster centroids,
聚类中心的总数
and this lowercase K's
这个小写的k
a number between one and
是第一个到第K个中心
capital K. I'm just using
中的一个
lower case K to index
我用小写的k
into my different cluster centroids.
表示不同聚类中心的下标
Next is lower case k. So
这是个小写k
that's the distance between the example and the cluster centroid
这就是某个样本到聚类中心的距离
and so what I'm going to
接下来
do is find the value
我要做的是
of K, of lower case
找出小写的k的值
k that minimizes this, and
让这个式子最小
so the value of
那么
k that minimizes you know,
接下来
that's what I'm going to
我就要将 c(i)
set as Ci, and
赋值为k
by convention here I've written
我这里按照惯例表示
the distance between Xi and
x(i) 和聚类中心的距离
the cluster centroid, by convention
因为出于惯例
people actually tend to write this as the squared distance.
人们更喜欢用距离的平方来表示
So we think of Ci as picking
所以我们可以认为
the cluster centroid with the smallest
c(i) 是距样本 x(i) 的距离的平方
squared distance to my training example Xi.
最小的那个聚类中心
But of course minimizing squared distance,
当然
and minimizing distance that should
使距离的平方最小或是距离最小
give you the same value of Ci,
都能让我们得到相同的 c(i)
but we usually put in the
但是我们通常还是
square there, just as the
写成距离的平方
convention that people use for K means.
因为这是约定俗成的
So that was the cluster assignment step.
这就是簇分配
The other in the loop
K均值循环中的另一部分是
of K means does the move centroid step.
移动聚类中心
And what that does is for
这是说
each of my cluster centroids, so
对于每个聚类中心
for lower case k equals 1 through
也就是说
K, it sets Mu-k equals
小写k从1循环到K
to the average of the points assigned to cluster.
将 μk 赋值为这个簇的均值
So as a concrete example, let's say
举个例子
that one of my cluster
某一个聚类中心
centroids, let's say cluster centroid
比如说是 μ2
two, has training examples,
被分配了一些训练样本
you know, 1, 5, 6, and 10 assigned to it.
像是1,5,6,10
And what this means is,
这个表明
really this means that C1 equals
c(1) 等于2
to C5 equals to
c(5) 等于2
C6 equals to and
c(6) 等于2
similarly well c10 equals, too, right?
同样的 c(10) 也是等于2 对吧?
If we got that
如果我们从上一步
from the cluster assignment step, then
也就是簇分配那一步得到了这些
that means examples 1,5,6 and
这个表明
10 were assigned to the cluster centroid two.
样本1 5 6 10被分配给了聚类中心2
Then in this move centroid step,
然后在移动聚类中心这一步中
what I'm going to do is just
我们要做的是
compute the average of these four things.
计算出这四个的平均值
So X1 plus X5 plus X6
即
plus X10.
计算 x(1)+x(5)+x(6)+x(10)
And now I'm going
然后计算
to average them so here I
它们的平均值
have four points assigned to
这里聚类中心有
this cluster centroid, just take
4个点
one quarter of that.
那么我们要计算和的四分之一
And now Mu2 is going to
这时μ2就是一个
be an n-dimensional vector.
n维的向量
Because each of these
因为
example x1, x5, x6, x10
x(1) x(5) x(6) x(10) 都是
each of them were an n-dimensional
n维的向量
vector, and I'm going to
然后
add up these things and, you
把这些相加
know, divide by four because I
再除以4
have four points assigned to this
因为
cluster centroid, I end up
有4个点分配到了这个聚类中心
with my move centroid step,
这样聚类中心μ2的移动
for my cluster centroid mu-2.
就结束了
This has the effect of moving
这个作用是说
mu-2 to the average of
将μ2移动到
the four points listed here.
这四个点的均值处
One thing that I've asked is, well here we said, let's
我要问的问题是
let mu-k be the average of the points assigned to the cluster.
既然我们要让μk移动到分配给它的那些点的均值处
But what if there is
那么如果
a cluster centroid no points
存在一个
with zero points assigned to it.
没有点分配给它的聚类中心 那怎么办?
In that case the more common
通常在这种情况下
thing to do is to just
我们就直接移除
eliminate that cluster centroid.
那个聚类中心
And if you do that, you end
如果这么做了
up with K minus one clusters
最终将会得到K-1个簇
instead of k clusters.
而不是K个簇
Sometimes if you really need
如果就是要K个簇
k clusters, then the other
不多不少
thing you can do if you
但是有个
have a cluster centroid with no
没有点分配给它的聚类中心
points assigned to it is you can
你所要做的是
just randomly reinitialize that cluster
重新随机找一个聚类中心
centroid, but it's more
但是直接移除那个中心
common to just eliminate a
是更为常见的方法
cluster if somewhere during
当你遇到了一个
K means it with no points
没有分配点的
assigned to that cluster centroid, and
聚类中心
that can happen, altthough in practice
不过在实际过程中
it happens not that often.
这个问题不会经常出现
So that's the K means Algorithm.
这就是K均值算法
Before wrapping up this video
在这个视频结束之前
I just want to tell you
我还想告诉你
about one other common application
K均值的
of K Means and that's
另外一个常见应用
to the problems with non well separated clusters.
应对没有很好分开的簇
Here's what I mean.
我指的是这个
So far we've been picturing K Means
到目前为止
and applying it to data
我们的K均值算法
sets like that shown here where
都是基于一些像图中所示的数据
we have three pretty
有很好的隔离开来的
well separated clusters, and we'd
三个簇
like an algorithm to find maybe the 3 clusters for us.
然后我们就用这个算法找出三个簇
But it turns out that
但是事实是
very often K Means is also
K均值经常会用于
applied to data sets that
一些这样的数据
look like this where there may
看起来并没有
not be several very
很好的分来的
well separated clusters.
几个簇
Here is an example application, to t-shirt sizing.
这是一个应用的例子 关于T恤的大小
Let's say you are a t-shirt
假设你是T恤制造商
manufacturer you've done is you've gone
你找到了一些人
to the population that you
想把T恤卖给他们
want to sell t-shirts to, and
然后
you've collected a number of
你搜集了一些
examples of the height and weight
这些人的
of these people in your
身高和体重的数据
population and so, well I
我猜
guess height and weight tend to
身高体重更重要一些
be positively highlighted so maybe
然后你可能
you end up with a data
收集到了这样的样本
set like this, you know, with
一些关于
a sample or set of
人们身高和体重的样本
examples of different peoples heights and weight.
就像这个图所表示的
Let's say you want to size your t shirts.
然后你想确定一下T恤的大小
Let's say I want to design
假设我们要设计
and sell t shirts of three
三种不同大小的t恤
sizes, small, medium and large.
小号 中号 和大号
So how big should I make my small one?
那么小号应该是多大的?
How big should I my medium?
中号呢?
And how big should I make my large t-shirts.
大号呢?
One way to do that would
有一种
to be to run my k means
在这样的数据上
clustering logarithm on this data
使用K均值算法进行聚类
set that I have shown on
的方法就像我展示的那样